[Music]
[Applause]
one thing i will never understand in
this industry is why everyone bashes the
smith machine so much
it's just like a weird overreaction to
me
so you'll hear coaches bash unstable
surface training
they will rightfully point out that if
you're trying to produce force you need
a stable environment you know
popular saying in our industry is you
can't shoot a cannon out of a canoe so
unstable training over here is bad so
more stable is better but up until point
because if you go too stable
like with a smith machine that's also
bad so free weights are in the middle
they're perfect but unstable is bad and
too stable is bad
could it be that stable training like
really stable like a smith machine
is even better for certain situations
anyone anyone i'm a biomechanics geek
and i'm an aficionado of strength
training so i love every exercise
i'm just a big fan of movements
bodybuilding powerlifting strong man
olympic weightlifting crossfit
like i like every strength sport strong
lifting
i like every movement i love every
exercise a good carpenter is going to
have a big tool belt
yes you're going to use your hammer and
your screwdriver
a lot more than you use some specialty
tool but you will use that specialty
tool from time to time when you train a
lot of people
and when you train yourself year round
you're going to need that specialty tool
a lot so the bigger your arsenal
the better off you'll be and while i'm a
huge fan of free weights i also like the
smith machine
several years ago i did a little
experiment i wanted to see if i could
maintain my squat strength
by just doing smith machine squats for
like four weeks or six weeks so yeah all
i did was tons of smith machine squats
but
i did it uniquely i didn't put my feet
in front of the bar like you see people
do and stay very upright and do like
hack squats i actually put my feet right
under the bar
just like you do in a normal squat and i
made my form very similar to my regular
back squat but this smooth machine
allowed me to stay more upright and not
shoot my hips up as much and i think it
worked my quads
a little extra because when i went back
to the freeway squat i did feel
uncoordinated but i set a pr
like i pr from doing smith machine
squats so yes i've seen the research
that shows decreased muscle activity but
the experiments i've done with smith
machine
show the same muscle activity and in
some cases greater activity same with
the plate loaded lever machines
so it could be that in these cases where
there's a discrepancy in the literature
the
the researchers don't quite know how to
position the lifter optimally to
maximize muscle activation
nevertheless i do like free weights more
than the smith machine
and plate loaded machines but that
doesn't mean that machines aren't still
awesome
you know i have so many clients that
prefer to do lunges off the smith
machine
what's wrong with that hip thrust off
the smith machine why wouldn't you let
them
trainers this day and age will be like
those aren't functional trust me your
client does not care if something's
functional or not if someone trains with
you and they don't become more
functional
you're a pretty bad trainer i mean even
if you have them doing all smith machine
exercises
they're going to become more functional
but they didn't come to you to be more
functional
most of them come to you wanting to look
better and to help somebody look
better in my opinion you would want to
use a lot of different tools you know
barbells dumbbells kettlebells bands
machines so i do love my machines and i
especially like them for glute training
i think the smith machine is awesome for
glute training i have an angled smith
machine
in glute lab san diego and i have a
vertical smith machine in glute lab las
vegas
so there are a lot of great glute
exercises that you can indeed do off the
smith machine
and i filmed 30 of them so for this
video we're going to roll through all 30
exercises
and i'll just do a voiceover alright
first i want to show you how i lock the
bar in place
just using a simple band now first up
we've got the
lying leg press this replaces a line
like a vertical leg press machine
now we've got the deficit stiff legged
deadlift
staying on a block there to increase the
range of motion
and increase the stretch on the
hamstrings
okay next up we have the good morning
and notice with this because of the
angled smith machine she can just keep
sitting back further and further so her
shin angle becomes negative it's more of
an angle than vertical
now we've got the b stance rdl
remember with b stance you want 70
percent load on that front foot
30 percent on the back foot all right
followed up by the single leg
stiff legged deadlift she lets the bar
drift out in front slightly
this is actually really challenging but
this is a huge stretch on that hamstring
right now we've got the frog kick all
right say what you want looks weird but
some women love this exercise
you've got to have that bar locked into
place if you do this though
all right followed by the quadruped hip
extension you're on all fours
look at that range though she's kicking
tall there
again you got to have that bar locked
into place to do these
and then this is the sideline hip raise
this is hard enough to do with body
weight adding extra load makes it brutal
and see how she's on a pad that gives
her even more range of motion
right now we've got the box squat what i
like about this is that it teaches you
how to really spread your legs
and start from a dead stop at the bottom
all right followed up by the sumo
deadlift
what i like about this is this is kind
of like a a block pull or a rack pull
you don't go
quite as deep so you can use heavier
load
all right now my favorite the hip thrust
i do these all the time these are one of
my favorite and i like the angled smith
machines
best for these next up we've got the bee
stance hip thrust
on this one you want 70 of the load on
the left foot the
back foot and 30 on the front foot
next up the single leg hip dust this is
really hard with a plate on each side
you can kind of see actually heaving it
might be a little too heavy there
all right now we've got the dual
elevated hip thrust with both the
shoulders and feet elevated
this works the hamstrings more and it
gets more hit range of motion
from the hips these are surprisingly
challenging
all right now we've got the glute bridge
and this is with a narrow stance glute
bridge you just need a bench
followed by the smith machine frog pump
these are a staple
we do these all the time notice the
heels are together but not the front of
the feet
and we do these for very high reps all
right next up
is the wide stance glute bridge we put
two benches of equal height
this allows for a wide stance and some
people love this one
all right now we've got the single leg
glute bridge
again this is like a lot more
challenging than it looks
you need good hamstring flexibility to
even do that and then here we've got a
frog pump variation
uh the frog thrust and these work really
well
and if you've got an incline bench it
works wonders
all right now we've got the squat
and what i like about this squat is with
the angled machine it keeps you very
upright
see at the bottom how upright she is
forces more work onto the quads
and the next step we've got the front
squat which is brutal
or using a plate on each side is really
hard if you go deep
and again keeps you nice and upright
okay now we've got the b stance squat
this one i like because it's nice and
stable and
you try to keep 70 load on the front
foot 30 on the rear foot
all right followed up by the kneeling
squat
and i like doing these off a smith
machine compared to a barbell
but some people love those they get
surprisingly high glute activity
all right followed up by the reverse
lunge
in this one she's leaning a lot to
increase the hip and decrease the knee
efforts all right followed by the front
reverse lunge
and this i like the front reverse lunge
it keeps you even more honest
making you work the legs harder all
right now we've got a curtsy lunge
this increases the stretch on that rear
glute
i like to do those alternating right
now we've got the leaning lunge you use
a pad
lean into it i don't particularly like
these very much what some of my clients
do
you're working the outer leg on those
all right you've got
a step up and this one i like because
some people fail to squat at the top
half
notice this isn't a lot of range of
motion so it strengthens the top half of
that
in contrast here's the zercher deficit
reverse lunge from a really tall bench
look how deep she goes look how much
stretch she gets on the glute
and that zurcher position keeps you nice
and upright
these are surprisingly effective give
those a try
and finally we've got the bulgarian
split squat she has got laces down on
that on the back foot
and these are amazing for the legs and
glutes
so now you've seen the 30 exercises i
hope you enjoy the video i hope you
learned something new i hope this gave
you some new ideas in your training and
i hope it opened your mind
to the smith machine being pretty darn
awesome it's okay to like the barbell
and the smith machine
it's not like you have to choose the
smith machine isn't going to be mad if
you like the barbell and the barbell
won't be mad if you like the smith
machine
you can like them both personally i
prefer doing
smith machine hip thrust and smith
machine lunges over their barbell
counterparts
most of my clients prefer the barbell
but that's just me
so give some of these movements a try
and let me know what you think in the
comments section if you like what you
saw
please hit like please make sure you
subscribe to my channel and leave me a
comment on what you'd like to see next
i'm always looking for new ideas thank
you for tuning in i've got a lot of
exciting stuff for 2021
we've just gotten started if this video
intrigued you
and you would like to train under my
system using my principles
then i invite you to click on the link
below and subscribe to booty by brett
and join the thousands of other happy
members who are seeing amazing results